Fernando Augusto Constantino da Silva

Curitiba – PR – Brazil https://fconstantino.me

const.fernando@gmail.com +55 (42) 998 120 619

Bachelor of Electronic Engineering (2017), fluent in English, 8 years of professional development experience in different backend and frontend technologies. Familiar with microservices (docker and Kubernetes). Already worked in projects of Windows (Apache/IIS) and Linux (Apache/nginx) services, implemented on local, shared (cPanel/CMS), and dedicated environments (AWS EC2+RDS+EBS+S3).

Currently working with an agile squad-based global development team aligning goals and strategies with other squads from different countries, applying SOLID and clean code design strategies.

As a leader, coordinated an IT DevOps team working from hardware and infrastructure maintenance to software development and user support, having coordinated internal HR processes and KPI planning. Now a champion in APIs, defining strategies and design patterns for RESTful APIs that are used cross-projects at a company level, delivering code that's daily used by hundreds of thousands of people around the world.

Some personal characteristics include excellent interpersonal communication, easy learning, proactivity, and creativity. Interest in innovation and technology.

Formation

- Master's degree (Strictu Sensu) in Electric Engineering at UTFPR-PG, with a research focused on computational intelligence applied to control systems, using Python to create a time-based railway environment simulation framework and implementing different bioinspired metaheuristics as controllers for performance comparison.
- Graduation (Bachelor) in Electronics and Communications Engineering, with final paper applied to flight stability control of a drone with AI. UTFPR-PG, completion in 2017.
- Supplementary courses: Industrial Robotics (UTFPR, 2013), FPGA (UTFPR, 2015), Fuzzy Logic (UTFPR, 2014), Hardware (CEBRAC, 2011), English (FISK, 2011), 3DStudio and AutoCAD (Training, 2007) Webdesign (CEBRAC, 2005).

Experience

- 2019-Present Software Development Engineer at CrossKnowledge A Wiley Brand acting in an agile squad-based global team, participating and presenting Scrum ceremonies (daily, reviews, retrospective, refinement, and planning) and aligning goals and strategies with other squads from different countries. Works with different products and stacks for both frontend (Vue.js, Gulp, Webpack, SASS) and backend (Symfony, PHPUnit, Django, Node.js), managing tasks in JIRA and SVN releases.
- 2017-2019 IT Coordinator at FATEB (Telêmaco Borba Faculty), leading a DevOps team composed of 5 members, responsible for projects and maintenance of infrastructure (IT, surveillance, multimedia, and telecommunications) for 2k+ simultaneous users (locally and remotely), support for external systems (TOTVS RM ERP, Moodle, SAGAH), internal systems development (PHP + MySQL + MSSQL intranet integrated with other external systems) and server virtualization (VirtualBox, VMWare).
- 2015-2017 Full Stack Developer at MaisEmpresa, responsible for the development of an ERP system framework (PHP + JS + MySQL + Docker) with GIT SVN in an AWS environment (EC2 + S3 + RDS).
- 2014-2015 Electronic Engineer at Kahton Agrotechnology, responsible for the development of agricultural automation and electronic maintenance projects (identification of problems and replacement of THT and SMD components).

2012-2013 - Paid Internship as Electronics Technician, with a weekly working load of 20 hours, working in the support and maintenance of electronic equipment (LCD monitors, ATX PSUs, and motherboards) in the Information Technology Management Coordination (COGETI) at UTFPR-PG.

Additional Activities

- Maintains a personal server with a stack of microservices containers that includes reverse
 proxying (nginx), mail handling (postfix + dovecot + rainloop), health checking (netdata),
 database (Postgres), SSL certificates management (letsencrypt), caching (Redis) and a
 dedicated cronjob manager. Hosts personal projects and websites.
- Developed a tendering management website on early 2010 that's still functional (PHP + MySQL + Apache stack), being updated to a Python (*Django*) + *nginx* stack, having peaks of 10k+ daily hits.
- Designed and implemented a wired and wireless logical network infrastructure (computer + surveillance + telephony, with structured cabling) for 2,000 concurrent users with external access points (VPN) using Ubiquiti / Mikrotik / TP-Link equipment.
- Developed a Fuzzy Logic algorithm (MATLAB) for power grid protection systems based on live meteorological data.
- Developed an AI algorithm (comparing classical method in MATLAB and RNN with TensorFlow in Python) for recognition of vehicle plates in surveillance camera images.
- Developed a mobile application for Android and a hardware device that communicated with each other through Bluetooth, implementing a custom firmware that encoded real-time sensors data that were displayed in a graph in the app.
- Experienced in hardware systems design (ATMEGA, ARM, Microchip, Altera FPGA) with low-level programming (C, Assembly).

Other Information

- Conducted a volunteer project with another engineer during 2016-2017 teaching programming basics to public school students (aging 12~15) at Cesar P. Martinez Institute of Education, using simple electric experiments to introduce the digital world.
- President of Protut Electrical Engineering Junior Company, 2014-2015, leading strategic decisions and positioning. Coordinated the implementation of management systems (5S, 5W2H, and PDCA) in different departments.
- CPO of Protut Electrical Engineering Junior Company, 2013-2014, leading a team of 4
 members responsible for the development and implementation of projects (noise control
 device for libraries, cellular signal blocker, X-ray machine maintenance, small business
 desktop management system and chemical laboratories electronic equipment maintenance).
- Coordinator of the UTFPR-PG Extension Knowledge Project Coordinator, from 11/2012 to 05/2013, which later became the Protut Electrical Engineering Junior Company, managing projects and doing the intermediary with teachers for follow-up and consulting.
- Acted as a volunteer in AFS Intercultural Programs (BR-SP2 Regional), conducting administrative processes and as a counselor of incoming exchange students, helping in the setting of the same.
- Ministered courses in the area of Printed Circuit Boards and Computer Aided Engineering Projects in 2015, 2016 and 2017 at UTFPR-PG.
- Driver's License category AB (regular non-profitable cars and motorcycles).
- Loves trains, photography, and DIYs. 26 years old, willing to have an intercultural experience living abroad.